Guide to the J.S. Holliday Research Collection on the William Swain Family
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
J. S. Holliday research collection on the William Swain family
1799-1980
WA MSS S-2408
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.77
(9 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
J.S. Holliday's collection relating to the Swain family acquired while doing research for his book The World Rushed In. The collection includes 27 letters from Sabrina and George to William, dated April 15, 1849 to September 8, 1850. Also included are "A Forty Niner," William's dictated recollections, and his will, made out before leaving for California. Other family papers include William's father Isaac's account books, letters of family members and neighbors, and a daguerreotype and cased albumen prints, presumably of family members. Holliday's research files include approximately 150 letters from Sara Swain to Holliday and another 70 to her Mormon cousin Nancy Williams, with much information on the Swain family and Niagara County, New York. These are accompanied by Holliday's notes, transcripts of the Swain letters, photocopies of materials related to the Wolverine Rangers, Edward Eberstadt's notes, Sara Swain's notes on family and local history, and After 100 Years, Nancy Williams' biography of Rebecca and Frederick Granger Williams.
Holliday, J. S.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Yerba Buena Books on the Frederick W. Beinecke Fund, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 9: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
William Swain Journals and Letters (WA MSS 466)
J. S. HOLLIDAY AND THE WILLIAM SWAIN FAMILY
J. S. Holliday's gold rush history, The World Rushed In: The California Gold Rush Experience (New York: Simon and Schuster, c1981), is based in large part on the experiences of forty-niner William Swain. Swain was born in Youngstown, New York in 1821, the second son of Isaac and Patience Swain. He taught school from 1844 to 1846, and married Sabrina Swain in 1847. Their first child, Lila Crandall Swain, was born in June 1848. When the gold discoveries in California were announced at the end of 1848, William decided to go to California. At Independence, Missouri, they joined a company of men from Marshall, Michigan, the Wolverine Rangers. In May 1849 they started on their overland journey, reaching California in November of that year. A year later, Swain started for home via Panama, reaching New York in February 1851.
J. S. Holliday was introduced to the William Swain journals and letters by Edward Eberstadt, the New York rare book and manuscript dealer who had acquired them from William Swain's daughter Sara Sabrina Swain. Eberstadt had intended to publish the journal and diary but had been unable to do so due to the press of business and ill health, and asked Holliday, a recent Yale graduate, to take over the project. Holliday did so, and met Sara Swain in 1948. Born in 1860, Sara was a school teacher and amateur historian of Niagara County, New York. Holliday discovered that she still held letters that her mother Sabrina and uncle George had sent to her father during the gold rush. Sara gave Holliday the letters, which form part of the present collection, in 1951. She died in 1953.
The Swain collection includes documents concerning William Swain's father, Isaac, who had first been married to Elizabeth Hall. Their daughter, Rebecca, married Frederick Granger Williams, who was a counselor to Joseph Smith. The Williams family followed Joseph Smith to Illinois and Missouri and made the overland journey to the Salt Lake Valley in 1847. Her grandson, Frederick Granger Williams, married Nancy Clement, who later corresponded with Sara Sabrina Swain.
Scope and Contents
The J. S. Holliday Research Collection on the William Swain Family consists of papers relating to the Swain family, which Holliday gathered in the course of his research for The World Rushed In. The collection is housed in eight boxes and is organized into two series: Swain Family Papers and J. S. Holliday Research Files.
Series I, Swain Family Papers, 1862-1980, boxes 1-3, is organized into five subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Documents and Financial Papers, Other Papers, and Photographs. The correspondence includes 27 letters to forty-niner William Swain from his wife Sabrina and brother George, dated April 15, 1849 to September 8, 1850. Also included are "A Forty Niner," William's dictated recollections, and his will, made out before leaving for California. Other family papers include William's father Isaac's account books, letters of family members and neighbors, including a draft of a letter to William's half-sister Rebecca Swain Williams in 1839 announcing the death of Isaac and the family's reaction to Rebecca's conversion to Mormonism, and a daguerreotype and cased albumen prints, presumably of family members.
Series II, J. S. Holliday Research Files, 1862-1980, boxes 4-8, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Printed Material, and Other Papers. The files include approximately 150 letters from Sara Swain to Holliday and another 70 to her Mormon cousin Nancy Williams, with much information on the history of the Swain family and Niagara County, New York. These are accompanied by Holliday's notes, transcripts of the Swain letters, photocopies of materials related to the Wolverine Rangers, Sara Swain's notes on family and local history, and After 100 Years, Nancy Williams' biography of Rebecca and Frederick Granger Williams.
Mormons -- United States; Overland journeys to the Pacific; Pioneers -- California -- Biography; California -- Gold discoveries; California -- History -- 1846-1850; Niagara County (N.Y.); Youngstown (N.Y.); Account books; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Photographic prints; Thermoplastic cases; Overland journeys to the Pacific -- 1849; Eberstadt, Edward, 1883-1958; Holliday, J. S.; Swain, George, 1819-1892; Swain, Isaac; Swain, Sara Sabrina; Swain, William, 1821-1904; Williams, Nancy Clement; Swain family -- Archives; Wolverine Rangers (Firm)
- Swain Family Papers, 1799-1927; Series I; 1.46; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Swain Family Papers, is organized into five subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Documents and Financial Papers, Other Papers, and Photographs.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters to William Swain
      - Swain, Sabrina and George, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      - Swain, Sabrina and George, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Other Letters
      - DeLand, Minerva to George Swain, 1871 May 21
      - Drown, George A. to Mike Conner, 1882 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Fralick, Abraham to E. J. Penniman, 1852 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Fralick, D. D. to E. J. Penniman, 1849 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Root, William J. to B. M. Root, 1862 Mar 11
      - Rudd, Sarah to [Isaac] Swain, 1836 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Swain, George to unidentified, 1852 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - [Swain,] Isaac to George, William, and Patience Swain, 1841 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Swain, Patience. Envelope addressed to her (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - [Swain, ----?] to Rebecca Swain Williams. Draft, 1839 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - [----?], Lorayne to George [Swain?], 1847 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - WRITINGS
    - [Swain, George?] "Description of the night of the 4th Feby. 1842." Holograph (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Swain, George. Diary, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Swain, William. "A Forty-niner." Holograph, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Dictated by Swain
    - [Swain, William?] Diary entry for March 25 detailing an inspection of his school, n.y. Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Commonplace book with poems, including one by Charles Swain, clippings, and extracts from Shakespeare (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - DOCUMENTS AND FINANCIAL PAPERS
    - L. Porter's promissory notes and receipts, many made out to Isaac Swain, 1799-1816 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Page of accounts from an unidentified account book, 1799-1801 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Isaac Swain. Account book, 1817-35 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Isaac and George Swain. Account book, 1834-46 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Statement of account. Robert Fox with Isaac [and George] Swain, 1838 Jun-Nov (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Agreement between George and William Swain and John McArthur. Draft, 1847 Apr 20
      Written on sheet of paper with school records
    - William Swain's will, 1849 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Advertisements for John B. Root's boilers and steam engines, [1867]
    - Poems by Cordelia Swain. Clippings, 1852, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Invitation to Jessie Cornwell's wedding, 1904 Sep 2 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Leaves from "Mother's Tree" at Locust Hill, 1927 Jul 4 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - William, Sabrina, and George Swain. Copy photographs (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Copies of daguerreotypes
    - William Swain. Copy photograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Swain house, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Swain house and trees in yard (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Unidentified man. Daguerreotype, ninth plate, in thermoplastic case (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Unidentified man, wearing glasses and reading a book. Carte-de-visite albumen photograph in case (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified younger man. Carte-de-visite albumen photograph in case, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified older man. Carte-de-visite albumen photograph in case, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified man. [Ambrotype?] in case, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
- J. S. Holliday Research Files, 1862-1980; Series II; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  Series II, J. S. Holliday Research Files, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Printed Material, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Sara Swain Incoming
      - Charles, H. J., 1948 Aug 30
      - Girling, Jessie Swain, 1935 Dec 4 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Keating family, 1937, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Scovell, J. Boardman, 1948 Aug 19 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Swain, George, 1935 Dec 14 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Williams, Nancy, 1946, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Sara Swain Outgoing
      - Eberstadt, Edward
        - Letters, 1934-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Holliday, J. S.
        - Letters, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
        - Letters, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 49-50)
        - Letters, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 51-53)
        - Letters, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 54-57)
        - Letters, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 58-60)
        - Letters, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 61-62)
        - Letters, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Williams, Nancy
        - Letters, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 64)
        - Letters, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 65)
        - Letters, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 66)
        - Letters, 1938-40 (Box 5, Folder 67)
        - Letters, 1941-44 (Box 6, Folder 68)
        - Letters, 1945-46 (Box 6, Folder 69)
        - Letters, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 70)
        - Letters, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 71)
        - Letters, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 72)
        - Letters, 1950-51 (Box 6, Folder 73)
        - Letters, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 74)
        - Fragments, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 75)
      - Williams, Orlando
        - Letters, 1944-47 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Others
      - Barry, J. Neilson to James T. Babb, 1949
      - Eberstadt, Edward to Mr. [Poe?], 1939 Jul 13 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      - Girling, Jessie Swain to Nancy Williams, 1936 Mar 1 (Box 6, Folder 78)
      - Williams, Nancy to J. S. Holliday, [1953 Oct 17] (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - WRITINGS
    - Holliday, J. S.
      - "Biographical Notes." Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80)
      - "William Swain, 1821-1904." Typescript drafts (several), corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Swain, Sara S.
      - "Recollections." Recorded by J. S. Holliday, ca. 1950-51 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - "Daughter of Pioneer Youngstown Family Celebrates 90th Birthday." The Niagara Falls Gazette clipping, [1950 Jun] (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - National Society United States Daughters of 1812. 1892-1933 News-Letter. Volume 8, Number 4, 1934 Mar (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Swain, Sara Sabrina. "The Story of Laura Secord and Fanny Doyle. Heroines of the Niagara Frontier" (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Williams, Nancy C. After 100 Years. Independence, Missouri: Zion's Printing & Publishing Company, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - J. S. Holliday's Research Notes
      - William Swain diary and letters of William, Sabrina, and George Swain. Typescript, corrected (Box 7, Folder 87-88)
      - Copies of letters from Sabrina Swain to William Swain, made by Sara Swain, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - "Data on Isaac Swain", 1936-50, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - "Eberstadt's questions to Miss Swain and her answers", 1934, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 91)
      - "George Swain biographical info.", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 92)
      - "Info. from Niagara Co. histories", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 93)
      - "Miscellaneous info. on Swains & Youngstown residents, etc.", 1934, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 94)
      - "Notes by JSH on William's post-Gold Rush domestic life", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 95)
      - "Patience D. B. Swain - her early life. Info. on her children, Geo. & Wm. and her grandchildren", 1871, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 96)
        Includes letter from Minerva DeLand to George Swain, 1871 May 21
      - "Sabrina's geneology", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 97)
      - "Wolverine Rangers", 1862-1980, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 98-102)
        Includes letter from William J. Root to B. M. Root dated 1862 Mar 11; and advertisements for John B. Root's boilers and steam engines; a letter from H. J. Charles to Sara Swain dated 1948 Aug 30; a letter from Sarah Swain to J. S. Holliday dated 1948 Oct 17; a letter from J. Neilson Barry to James T. Babb dated 1949 Apr 1
      - Swain, Sara S. "Notes on Dunn & Swain Family - Also Early Settlers of Niag. and Porter Townships" (Box 8, Folder 103)
      - Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Other Papers
      - Jessie Swain Girling. Bank book, 1912-36 (Box 8, Folder 105)
- Oversize, 1847 Apr 20
  - Agreement between George and William Swain and John McArthur. Draft (from series I), 1847 Apr 20 (Box bsd, folder 106)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.21; (1 box)
  Box 9, Restricted Fragile, contains fragile originals. The materials are arranged in folder order and may only be seen with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been placed in the main files for reference use.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 5, folder 54 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Box 6, folder 81 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Box 6, folder 83 (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Box 7, folder 90 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Box 7, folder 91 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Box 7, folder 93 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Box 8, folder 98 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Box 8, folder 100 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Box 8, folder 101 (Box 9, Folder 115)